LORENZO NTIBARIKURE

Engineering Systems | Physical Modeling | Customer Focus

ntilau.github.io

in ntilau

ntilau

Findhoven, Netherlands

SUMMARY

My experiences, with a focus on numerical methods, encompass electronic and mechatronic system development and technical sales & support across several industries (Energy & Aerospace, Electronic Design Automation, and Semiconductors).

Leveraging such a background, I am currently helping designers to develop more effectively towards system-level compliance.

EXPERIENCE

Sr Engineer - Design Enablement

NXP Semiconductors

🗂 03/2022 - Present

Eindhoven, Netherlands

- Implemented electromagnetic simulation flows for SoCs development and electromagnetic interference predictions.
- Enhanced vendor solutions to meet the design and integration requirements of the cloud platform.
- Developed problem-resolution automation scripts and applied AI/ML algorithms for electromagnetic surrogate models.

Technical Account Manager

Ansys

- Utrecht, Netherlands
- Drove customer satisfaction by providing multi-disciplinary technical support and managing global presales activities involving the whole Ansys portfolio & ecosystem.
- Led teams to architect flows across disciplines, focusing on requirements and critical success factors.
- Advised global sales and account engineers on addressable initiatives and pipelines with preliminary requirements and solutions visions.

Sr. Applications Engineer

Ansys

- Utrecht, Netherlands
- Executed presales activities for electronic systems across industries, supporting highfrequency solutions and EMC flows across EMEA.
- · Led technical alignment with customers on automotive electrification and connectivity projects, successfully delivering consulting services and trainings.

Lead Engineer - Testing

Baker Hughes

□ 06/2013 - 12/2018

- ▼ Florence, Italy
- Led the development of industrial, ATEX compliant, distributed data acquisition systems to streamline tests execution timelines from months to weeks.
- Resolved 5+ electromagnetic interference issues in NPI validations and factory acceptance tests, contributing to best practices.
- Received an innovation award for patent disclosure of the Structural Vibration Monitoring System and multiple rewards for innovative solutions and customer impact.

Startup Co-founder

Università degli Studi di Firenze

Ö 06/2012 − 06/2013

Florence, Italy

• Initiated a spin-off, ElectroSoft, to provide efficient numerical codes for design problems.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Electronics Engineering

Università degli Studi di Firenze

School of "RF, Microwaves and Electromagnetics". Computational Methods focus. With grant (Jan 2011 - Jun 2013).

Master's Degree, Electronics Engineering

Università degli Studi di Firenze

Erasmus Placement/LLP framework thesis semester at Lehrstuhl für Theoretische Elektrotechnik, Universität des Saarlandes. With grant (Sep 2009 - Mar 2010).

Bachelor's degree, Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Università degli Studi di Firenze

☐ 01/2003 - 04/2008 Florence, Italy

AWARDS



EMEA TAM of the Year | Ansys (01/2021)

Award for customer and industry focus

Learn and adapt to win | BHGE (07/2018)

Patent impact award for the disclosure of "Module with sensors arrangement"

Customers determine our success | BHGE (03/2017)

Bronze award for the GE Aviation's Catalyst FETT advanced test instrumentation consulting

Customers determine our success | GE (10/2016)

Bronze award for the successful execution of the vibration monitoring system **ZADCO** customer structural vibrations acceptance tests

Learn and adapt to win | GE (03/2016) Bronze award for the co-generation plant cost savings on the SNC1-2 steam turbine performance validation

Learn and adapt to win | GE (10/2015)

Bronze award for the introduction and validation of an effective, cost-saving, structural vibrations digital integration algorithm aimed at accurately deriving speed & displacements measurements from ATEX-compliant accelerometers

External focus | GE (06/2014) • Led team promotion and value proposition pitches to business angels. Bronze award for the RCA activities on • Developed first opportunities in the defense industry. Cessao Onerosa, ADRE monitoring system EMI noise mitigation and customer assurance **Doctoral Researcher** Università degli Studi di Firenze Giorgio Barzilai Prize | SIEm (09/2012) **□** 01/2011 - 06/2013 Florence, Italy Best paper award for young researchers, for the work "Model order reduction in • Researched applied & computational electromagnetics, presenting 10+ papers, advis-Finite Element analysis of phased array ing student theses, and supporting examinations. antennas" presented at the XIX RiNEm • Developed a high-frequency electromagnetic 3D finite element C++ code for domain decomposition and nonlinear formulations. Ph.D. studies grant | UniFi (12/2010) Architected a methodology using MathWorks Simulink and Ansys HFSS for electro-Full tuition fees and allowance for remagnetic compatibility in variable speed drive systems. search on Electromagnetic Compatibility modeling techniques in variable speed drive systems - with GE/Nuovo Pignone Visiting Researcher Universität des Saarlandes Dean's listing | UniFi (04/2010) **1**0/2009 - 02/2010 Saarbrücken, Germany Commissione di Laurea Specialistica in Ingegneria Elettronica presieduta dal Prof. • Developed model order reduction in finite element analysis of antenna arrays for fast Piero Tortoli (Prot. 1051 n. class. III/9.1.2 and accurate beamforming. del 24 Maggio 2010) Implemented Matlab code for a 3000x matrix reduction and 300x speedup in antenna pattern computation LLP/Erasmus Placement grant | UniFl (10/2009)Thesis work semester relocation support **R&D** Engineer at Universität des Saarlandes Università degli Studi di Firenze **1**2/2007 - 03/2008 ▼ Florence, Italy CERTIFICATION • Developed wireless connectivity for a battery-powered avalanche rescue ground penetrating radar, optimizing firmware for fast full-duplex/half-duplex conversion timing. Professional Engineer, ID:ES2010277049000038 Executed the design and assembly of an ISM 868 MHz serial modem PCB prototype Università degli Studi di Firenze with off-the-shelf MCU and Radio (sub-GHz RFFE). • Achieved successful wireless system resulting in improved signal detection accuracy. **COURSES PROJECTS** Command of the Message Bearings loading test rig **Ansys** Baker Hughes, a GE Company □ 06/2020 Remote **Ö** 05/2018 - 12/2018 Florence, Italy JAWS: Just Another Way of Selling • Conceptual design of a novel bearings loading test rig aimed at validating bearings **Ansys** NTIs. □ 02/2020 Paris, France • Investigated on modeling methods of EM coupling between power (variable speed drive system) and signals cabling systems to predict potential interference issues. GE Crotonville: Delivering Customer Impact **GE** Aviation's Catalyst **GE Oil & Gas** Baker Hughes, a GE Company □ 03/2016 Munich, Germany **Ö** 06/2017 - 12/2018 Prague, Czech Republic Total Quality Lean Six Sigma Green Belt Led special instrumentation design and global technical reviews of FETT with design and testing teams (Czech Rep., Poland, USA, Canada). GE Oil & Gas • Contributed to >4 M\$ cross-P&L project and customer satisfaction. □ 06/2014 Florence, Italy **SKILLS** Gas Turbine embedded SAW sensors Baker Hughes, a GE Company Engineering Simulations Testing **Ö** 02/2018 - 12/2018 Florence, Italy Management Sales Strategy · Advised MSc thesis studed with University of Florence to investigate into SAW sen-Leadership **Customer Satisfaction** sors high frequency numerical modeling for accuracy control of temperature measurements. Finite Element Analysis Electronics Scripting Matlab Semiconductors LM9000: 65 MW aeroderivative gas turbine C Python Baker Hughes, a GE Company

Florence, Italy

• Contributed to conceptual instrumentation design and test rigs erection, data acquisi- LANGUAGES tion architecture and control system design by technical and HAZOP reviews. Cross'd **Ö** 01/2018 - 11/2018 Florence, Italy · Social networking app PoC based on Bluetooth Low Energy ranging. PoC with Apache Cordova and an AWS EC2 instance **BLE Asset Tracking Ö** 07/2017 - 09/2017 Florence, Italy Sub 5\$/Unit PoC of BLE tags (TI's CC2640) with firmware optimized for long-battery life, aimed at asset tracking and inventory management GE Power slip-ring digital telemetry Baker Hughes, a GE Company

Ö 04/2017 - 05/2017

Florence, Italy

- Ran Ansys HFSS simulations to optimize signal integrity over slip-ring connections (power supply and ethernet transmission lines)
- Achieved shrinking of the rings spacing leading to manufacturing costs reduction
- 4 weeks-FTE cross-P&L billing and customer satisfaction

Wet gas compressors at KLAB

GE Oil & Gas

□ 02/2016 - 06/2016

Haugesund, Norway

- Designed and procured validation equipment for ATEX zone 1 test bench.
- Developed Ex-d antenna and low noise amplifier system for GPS synchronization on NI's PXI systems.
- Managed IEC 60079-11 simple apparatus compliance on load cells upon using extremely low voltage (1.5 V) Ex-ia Wheatstone bridge conditioners.

Power density compressor

GE Oil & Gas

Ö 03/2014 - 05/2016

Florence, Italy

- Led the commissioning Fieldbus Foundation use in testing lab for more than 240 pressure transducers (0.1% uncertainty) upon identifing the proper Firmware configuration which enabled for massive and accurate pressure measurements.
- Managed capacitive vibration probes ATEX-compliance.
- Developed electrostatic numerical model to predict capacitance variation in various surroundings and target shape conditions.
- Contributed to DM37/08 compliance of the test rig contract specification, including power and signaling cabling selection and proper installation.

SNC1-2 steam turbine performance evaluation in 6.2 MW cogeneration plant **GE Oil & Gas**

Ö 09/2015 - 04/2016

Florence, Italy

- Defined novel pressure hookups method at lower cost and better performance to achieve accuracy controlled inter-stage enthalpy measurements according to ASME PTC 19.11.
- Programmed a CAN to Modbus TCP embedded module to enable static torque measurements on a MagCanica telemetry.

GE-6G PowerGen Module Structural Vibrations Monitoring System

GE Oil & Gas

11/2015 - 03/2016

Massa, Italy

Dutch	••••
English	••••
French	••••
German	••••
Italian	••••
Kirundi	••••
Spanish	••••

PUBLICATIONS

Patents

• L. Ntibarikure, "Module with sensors arrangement," US20180180464A1, 2018. [Online]. Available: https://patents.google. com/patent/US20180180464A1/en.

Books

 L. Ntibarikure. Contributions to the Art of Finite Elements in Electromagnetics. Florence. Italy, 2014. [Online]. Available: https://hdl. handle.net/2158/843133.

Journal Articles

- · L. Ntibarikure, "Multiphysics simulations for 5g rfics and socs," Bits&Chips, 2019.
- F. Barone, A. Signorini, L. Ntibarikure, T. Fiore, F. Di Pasquale, and C. J. Oton, "Fiberoptic liquid level sensing by temperature profiling with an fbg array," Sensors, vol. 18, no. 8, 2018. [Online]. Available: https:// www.mdpi.com/1424-8220/18/8/2422.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. S. and, "Harmonic balance domain decomposition finite elements for nonlinear passive microwave devices analysis," Electromagnetics, vol. 34, no. 3-4, pp. 239-252, 2014. DOI: 10.1080/02726343.2014.877756.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Efficient harmonic balance analysis of waveguide devices with nonlinear dielectrics," **IEEE Microwave and Wireless Components** Letters, vol. 22, no. 5, pp. 221-223, 2012. DOI: 10.1109/LMWC.2012.2192420.

Conference Proceedings

• L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Assessment of the performances of gmres(r) using a domain decomposition approach as a preconditioner," in Proceedings, XX Riunione Nazionale di Elettromagnetismo (XX RiNEm), Padua, Italy, 2014. [Online]. Available: https: //inspirehep.net/literature/1403858.

- Developped ATEX-compliant distributed acquisition system for more than 150 vibration measurement points, with 40 kHz analog bandwidth, WiFi5 backhaul to storage and real-time monitoring, with GPS or daisy-chain clock distribution synchronization
- Hands-on design of 3D assemblies and BOM for timely delivery and cost optimization of certified equipment in less than 4 months (vs typ. 8 months).
- Introduced and consolidated with third party metrology a software based velocity and displacement real-time computation from accelerometers, achieving direct \$150k savings, and subsequent lab processes OPEX benefits.
- Customer value delivered as onsite Turbomachinery Modules structural commissioning with patented solution

NovaLT16 gas turbine, bearings and cooling component tests

GE Oil & Gas

Ö 04/2014 - 10/2015

♥ Florence, Italy

- Design and validation of smartbox (field datalogger) for analog signals.
- Defined EMC-aware measurement loops design to achieve noise immunity and enhanced measurement accuracies, rigorously applying EN 61000 guidelines (CENELEC 25).

GE Aviation's GE9X High Pressure Compressor

GE Oil & Gas

Ö 01/2014 - 04/2014

Massa, Italy

- High density data acquisition system design for GE Aviation's compressor test in Massa.
- Performed mitigation on EMC noise due to 130 kW variable speed ventilation system

BCL306 and BCL317 centrifugal compressors rotordynamics

GE Oil & Gas

▼ Florence, Italy

Performed an Ex-p execution of stability's magnetic exciter, contributed to the resolution of customer's opened nonconformity on rotordynamic vibrations upon conducting an electromagnetic interference on Bently Nevada's 3500 RCA.

Finite Elements Software (FES)

Università degli Studi di Firenze

◆ Florence, Italy

 FES is an open source C++ framework for the development of "ad-hoc" simulation software aimed at a rapid implementation of novel numerical methods based on the Galerkin method. Core formulations validated reusing meshes from commercial packages (Comsol, HFSS)

Phased array antennas model order reduction

Universität des Saarlandes

10/2009 - 02/2010

Saarbrücken, Germany

- Developed in Matlab efficient near-to-far-fields formulations for fast electromagnetic radiation computation in large finite elements problems exploiting model order reduction with spectral interpolation for beam steering and pattern angles
- Modeled a large patch antenna array, assessing accuracy and performances through mesh/model export from Ansoft HFSS v11

RS-232 modem in ISM 868 MHz band

University of Florence

Ö 01/2007 - 04/2007

- ▼ Florence, Italy
- Designed and prototyped an 868 MHz wireless link for a ground penetration radar remote control over RS-232 protocol
- C-coded the PIC microcontroller FW and optimized in Assembly to garantee the fullduplex operation over half-duplex TI's CC1100 radio.
- Evaluated the performance of the wireless link in open field

- L. Ntibarikure, "Model order reduction in finite elements analysis of phased array antennas," in *Proceedings, XIX Riunione Nazionale* di Elettromagnetismo (XIX RiNEm), S. d. E. SiEm, Ed., Roma, Italy, 2012.
- L. Ntibarikure, G. Pelosi, and S. Selleri, "Harmonic balance finite element analysis of third order intermodulation products in ferrite devices," in *Proceedings, XIX Riunione Nazionale di Elettromagnetismo (XIX RiNEm)*, S. d. E. SiEm, Ed., Roma, Italy, 2012.

RECOMMENDATIONS

Mariano Morales

Senior Director, Global Technical Account Management @ Ansys (A Synopsys company)

**\begin{aligned}
\begin{aligned}
\begin{aligned}
23/05/2022
\end{aligned}**

Madrid, Spain

"During his tenure with Ansys, Laurent performed consistently above expectations He showed a tremendous ability to master new technology domains out of his comfort zone, to team up with colleagues from different functional groups and demonstrated an extreme customer focus that made him succesful. He is always eager to learn and evolve as a technical leader."

Tiziano Fiore

Head of Global Product Management @ ABB

Ö 09/09/2020

Helsinki, Finland

"Laurent is a brilliant engineer with entrepreneurial mindset. He approaches technical problems critically and with a deep knowledge of physics that allows him to handle any engineering challenge. Laurent is a great manager and a strong comunicator always willing to help others and share ideas and solutions with anyone in the team. I have learnt a lot from him, sitting side by side, working together on challenges in turbomachinery validation projects. I greatly recommend Laurent for business development and executive roles."